Okay, בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is ק"ח, kuf chet,
108. And we pick up at the bottom of ק"ז עמוד ב'.
kuf zayin amud bet. And we are dealing with the whole issue
of שחוטי חוץ, shechutei chutz, slaughtering and offering up sacrifices outside of
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Basically it is the איסור issur of
במות, bamot, the איסור issur of private altars, although it's not about
the having the altar, it's about using it. And we pick up
with איתמר. itmar. It is ק"ז עמוד ב' kuf zayin amud bet
about 10 lines before the lines get wide. איתמר, itmar, beginning of
the line. And here we go, practical application. In case anybody was
thinking of making an altar in their backyard this afternoon as a
nice summer project, you know, maybe instead of your like Fourth of
July barbecue, you want to do some offering on an altar. Let's
take a look. איתמר, itmar, it was taught, המעלה בזמן הזה, hama'aleh
b'zman hazeh, somebody who puts up sacrifices and burns them on an
altar nowadays. Okay, what's the story? רבי יוחנן אמר חייב. Rabbi Yochanan
amar chayav. You're חייב chayav for offering up sacrifices outside of the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and that's a חיוב כרת chiyuv kares as
we've been saying. ריש לקיש אמר פטור. Resh Lakish amar patur.
קרבן פסח?
Korban
Pesach?
No. Yeah, there's a question about קרבן פסח בזמן הזה Korban Pesach
b'zman hazeh but that would be in the מקום המקדש. Makom HaMikdash.
Okay? It
wouldn't be this? No. ריש לקיש אמר פטור. Resh Lakish amar patur.
רבי יוחנן אמר חייב. Rabbi Yochanan amar chayav. Why are you חייב?
chayav? קדושה ראשונה קידשה לשעתה וקידשה לעתיד לבוא. kedusha rishona kidsah l'sha'atah
v'kidsah l'atid lavo. The first sanctification of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
lasted for all future times and therefore that's still, even after it's
been destroyed, that still remains the central place and the only place
in which sacrifices are going to be acceptable. Now, I should qualify,
well, I'll just read ריש לקיש אמר פטור, Resh Lakish amar patur,
קדושה ראשונה קידשה לשעתה ולא קידשה לעתיד לבוא. kedusha rishona kidsah l'sha'atah
v'lo kidsah l'atid lavo. It wasn't for all future times. Now, there's
two points here. First of all, it's not really about קדושה ראשונה,
kedusha rishona, meaning even if you said that the second קדושה kedusha
was, you know, לעתיד לבוא, l'atid lavo, that would also be good.
Some people say for example רמב"ם Rambam says it by the קדושה
kedusha of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, that the first קדושה kedusha went
away
after the first exile, but then the second קדושה kedusha stays even
until today. So it's really not the question of the first קדושה
kedusha or the second one, does it last? It's really a question
of does either of the קדושה, kedusha, right, even if the first
one went away, maybe somehow for some reason the second one would
be stronger. Okay, so that's really the real question is does the
קדושה kedusha of the מקום המקדש Makom HaMikdash last until today? Whichever
קדושה kedusha it is sort of basing itself on. Now the other
point though to make is is that how much, and this is
a discussion that תוספות Tosfos says, because the גמרא Gemara says כי
לא באתם עד עתה אל המנוחה ואל
הנחלה. ki lo batem ad atah el hamenucha v'el hanachala. Right, המנוחה
hamenucha is נוב וגבעון, Nov v'Givon, whatever, שילה, Shiloh, ואל הנחלה v'el
hanachala that's ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay, that it could be that there's a
separate idea between the question of the קדושה kedusha ירושלים Yerushalayim or
the, I shouldn't just say ירושלים, Yerushalayim, the מקום המקדש, Makom HaMikdash,
and the איסור במות. issur bamot. It could be, right, the קדושה
kedusha is generally a question about about if that place retains its
sanctity, is it still possible for me to bring sacrifices there. As
Michael was just saying, let's say it's פסח Pesach and I want
to bring my ערב פסח, erev Pesach, I want to bring my
קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. Is it still can I bring my my
sacrifices there? Well, one question is even without a בית, bayit, even
though the בית bayit is destroyed, you know, maybe it's still a
place sanctified for bringing קרבנות. korbanot. Or you could say even if
I need a בית, bayit, okay, but when I'm going to get
around to building that בית, bayit, I don't need to resanctify it.
All right, so there's one question of is it sanctified and still
a place for bringing sacrifices. But in theory you could say, you
know what? If you brought you can't bring a sacrifice there. It's
got to be resanctified. But the whole idea that there was a
period of our history in which we were bringing sacrifices on a
private, you know, you know, we were bringing
sacrifices, everybody on their private במה, bamah, that was, as the פסוק
pasuk says, כי לא באתם עד עתה אל המנוחה ואל הנחלה. ki
lo batem ad atah el hamenucha v'el hanachala. That was a certain
transitional period in history until the מקום המקדש Makom HaMikdash had been
designated. Once that מקום המקדש Makom HaMikdash had been designated, this is
the place that God's שכינה, shchina, God has chosen for the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, then that means from that point on there's no
במות. bamot. It doesn't matter whether you can bring the, you know,
קרבנות korbanot in the מקום המקדש, Makom HaMikdash, whether it retains its
קדושה kedusha or not retains its קדושה. kedusha. We're out of that
transitional period. Everybody was allowed to do their own private thing, right,
during that transitional period. But once there was that central place that
was chosen to be the permanent place, it's now an איסור במות
issur bamot from here on in. So it's interesting to think about
that question. Is this really a function of מקום המקדש? Makom HaMikdash?
Now, it could be that it is for a technical reason. It
could be that if you bring a sacrifice, even ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish would agree that if you brought a sacrifice today in your
backyard, that you would have transgressed the איסור issur of bringing a
sacrifice outside of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, right? לא תוכל, lo
tuchal, you know, the גמרא Gemara before discussed the לאו, lav, right,
לא תעלה עלותיך בכל מקום אשר תראה, lo ta'aleh olotecha b'chol makom
asher tireh, what is that the
פסוק? pasuk? Anyways, so but whatever, anyway.
Anyway,
so ריש לקיש Reish Lakish could say the question is to be
חייב כרת, chayav karet, there’s a principle that it has to be
ראוי לפתח אהל מועד. roy lepesach ohel moed. To be חייב כרת
chayav kares. it says ואל פתח אהל מועד לא הביאו ve’el pesach
ohel moed lo heveio or לא יביאנו, lo yevieinu, right? So לא
הביאו. lo heveio. So I combined the two. Anyway, so therefore the
point could be like this. Maybe everybody agrees, once the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash was chosen, there’s of course an איסור במות. issur bamos.
Nobody’s allowed to bring sacrifices in their backyard. The question is are
you חייב, chayav חייב כרת chayav kares? for שחוטי חוץ? shchutei chutz?
And to be חייב chayav it has to be ראוי לפתח אהל
מועד. roy lepesach ohel moed. So therefore in that case רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan says, you know what? It is ראוי לפתח אהל מועד.
roy lepesach ohel moed. In theory you could go ahead and bring
it in the מקום המקדש. makom hamikdash. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like
this: לימא דבפלוגתא דרבי אליעזר ורבי
יהושע קמיפלגי. Naima de’biflugta de’Rabbi Eliezer ve’Rabbi Yehoshua kamifligi. Let’s say
this is a debate of
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. תנן, Nan, אמר
רבי אליעזר, amar Rabbi Eliezer, כשהיו בונים בהיכל, keshey’hayu bonim ba’heichal, when
they were building in the time of בית שני Bayis Sheini the
היכל, heichal, היו עושים קלעים בהיכל וקלעים בעזרות. hayu osim kelayim ba’heichal
ve’kelayim ba’azaros. They would make these curtains around the היכל heichal where
they were going to build the walls of the היכל, heichal, and
curtains around where they were going to build the עזרה, azara, the,
you know, the walls of the עזרה. azara. אלא שבהיכל בונים מבחוץ,
Ela shebeheichal bonim mibachutz, but in the היכל heichal they would build
on the outside of the curtain because you didn’t want to be
standing in the place where the היכל heichal would be, so you
were building the wall and you were standing outside the space that
the wall was sort of, you know, encircling.
ובעזרה בונים מבפנים, Uva’azara bonim mifnim, but in the עזרה azara they
would be able to, you know, the curtain would be on the
outside and they’d build the wall on the inside of the curtain.
אמר רבי יהושע, Amar Rabbi Yehoshua, fine. שמעתי שהיו מקריבים אף על
פי שאין בית, Shamati she’hayu makrivim af al pi she’ein bayis, ואוכלים
קדשי קדשים אף על פי שאין קלעים, ve’ochlim kodshu kodoshim af al
pi she’ein kelayim, וקדשים קלים ומעשר שני אף על פי שאין חומה.
ve’kodshim kalim u’maaser sheini af al pi she’ein chomah.
I heard that you can bring קרבנות korbanos without a בית, bayis,
so this clearly means even now you can bring קרבנות korbanos because
the קדושה kedusha remains. Again, this is a second level of a
חידוש. chiddush. Just because the קדושה kedusha remains doesn’t mean you don’t
need the structure of a בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, you know,
as I said, the קדושה kedusha could remain and it could mean
when you rebuild the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash you don’t have to
resanctify it. But he says no, the קדושה kedusha remains to the
point that even without that structure since the destruction of the מקדש,
mikdash, nice thing to be learning right after תשעה באב, Tisha B’av,
since the destruction of the מקדש mikdash meant the קדושה kedusha didn’t
go off, that means you could keep on doing what you were
doing even before there was a מקדש, mikdash, a בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash there. Okay? And you could go ahead and bring קרבנות korbanos
even without it, and you could eat קדשי קדשים kodshu kodoshim even
though there are not walls or curtains to define the space of
the עזרה, azara, okay? The fact that you’re still eating במקום העזרה
bemakom ha’azara is significant and it doesn’t need a wall to define
it as מקום העזרה. makom ha’azara. And you could eat קדשים קלים
kodshim kalim and מעשר שני maaser sheini in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you don’t
need a wall around ירושלים Yerushalayim to define it as the sort
of עזרת ישראל ezras Yisrael and the קדושת ירושלים. kedushas Yerushalayim. מפני
שקדושה ראשונה קידשה לשעתה וקידשה לעתיד לבוא. Mipnei shekedusha rishona kidsha leshaita
vekidsha le’asid lavo.
Okay,
so therefore, so
clearly רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua holds that the קדושה kedusha remains to
so much of the point that you don’t even need a structure.
So the גמרא Gemara says now what is, how about רבי אליעזר?
Rabbi Eliezer? לאו מכלל דרבי אליעזר סבר לא קידשה? Lav miklal deRabbi
Eliezer savar lo kidsha? So presumably when רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer emphasizes
that you would have קלעים kelayim when they would build it, and
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says back, oh no, you don’t need קלעים,
kelayim, it sounds like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer holds that it’s not
sanctified and therefore you need to resanctify it, you’re going to need
some form of a wall and somewhat. So the גמרא Gemara says,
right, אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי, amar leh Ravina le'Rav Ashi, ממי,
mimai,
where do you get that from? דילמא דכולי עלמא קדושה ראשונה קידשה
לשעתה וקידשה לעתיד לבוא. Dilma de’kulei alma kedusha rishona kidsha le’shaita ve’kidsha
le’asid lavo. Nobody is disagreeing, everybody agrees to the principle of רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua that you could be מקריב makriv without a בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash and so on. מר מאי דשמיע ליה קאמר ומר
מאי דשמיע ליה קאמר. Mar mai dishmei lei ka’amar u’mar mai dishmei
lei ka’amar. Each passing down related traditions. וכי תימא קלעים לרבי אליעזר
למה לי? Ve’chi teima kelayim l’Rabbi Eliezer loma lei? So
why do you need curtains since you don’t need the curtains to
allow you to eat the קרבנות korbanos or to be מקריב makriv
the קרבנות korbanos or
whatever? לצניעותא בעלמא. Litzni’usa be’alma. As a sense of modesty, you know,
you don’t want to have a big wide open space and you
know like you go right now and you know in front of
a building and they’re building something and they put up, they put
up a wall so people don’t see the whole ground being torn
up and so on. Okay, and it’s respectful for מקום המקדש. makom
hamikdash. Fine. So that was the end of it, okay? That was
the whole discussion of whether you’re חייב כרת chayav kares, for bringing
a קרבן korban in your backyard, was that debate of רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, whether קדושה ראשונה קידשה לשעתה,
kedusha rishona kidsha leshaita, and as I said, even for ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish who says you’re not חייב chayav, does not mean that
there’s no longer an איסור במות, issur bamos, it could be that
there is an איסור במות, issur bamos, but part of the חיוב
chiyuv is אל פתח אהל מועד לא הביאו, al pesach ohel moed
lo heveio, that it’s ראוי לפתח אהל מועד. roy lepesach ohel moed.
The גמרא Gemara doesn’t sort of spell it out. Okay, now we
move on to another topic.
But according to רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua then there'd be no problem
going on הר הבית Har Habayit today.
Yeah, that's why people want to bring a קרבן פסח. korban pesach.
I mean, there's a question about טומאה, tumah, but if it's something
like קרבן פסח וטומאה הותרה בציבור korban pesach v'tumah hutra b'tzibbur exactly.
Okay, איתמר Itmar was taught. המעלה ואין בו כזית. Hamaleh v'ein bo
kezayit. Let's say you put something up on the fire and you
need a כזית kezayit to be חייב כרת, chayav kares. okay? And
the thing you put up, this little piece of the animal, it's
not a כזית kezayit worth, ועצם משלימה לכזית. v'etzem mashlima l'kezayit. But
it's got a little bone in it, so you put up a
little פלייש fleisch or something because we learned birds were חייב chayav
before. Okay, or you put up like a פולקע pulkha and the
actual meat on it isn't a כזית, kezayit, but with the bone
it is a כזית. kezayit. Okay, רבי יוחנן אמר חייב וריש לקיש
אמר פטור. Rabbi Yochanan amar chayav v'Resh Lakish amar pattur. Debate of
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש. Resh Lakish. רבי יוחנן אמר
חייב, Rabbi Yochanan amar chayav, חיבור עולין כעולין דמי, chibbur olin k'olin
dami, something connected to something that is offered up is considered like
a part of it. As רש״י Rashi points out, the related thing
to, the exact related discussion here is what we discussed a while
ago which is, as long as the bone is connected to the
meat, you would put the bone, you would burn it together with
the meat. Whereas if it's separated of like an עולה olah let's
say, you would not have to put a separate bone up on
the fire. So here it's still connected. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says
as long as it's still connected it counts as a part of
what is offered up.
ריש לקיש אמר פטור, Resh Lakish amar pattur, you're פטור. pattur. חיבור
עולין לאו כעולין דמי. chibbur olin lav k'olin dami. It's true that
you burn it if it's connected, but it doesn't mean that it
is seen as a thing that is offered. Okay, it's just put
up because it's being schlepped along together with the meat. It never
is per se the thing that is offered even when it is
combined and therefore you're not חייב chayav for offering up a כזית.
kezayit. Okay, איבעיא להו רבא. Iba'ya leh Rava. Now רבא Rava asked,
המעלה Hamaleh top of קח עמוד א, kuf chet amud alef, ראש
בן יונה שאין בו כזית, rosh ben yonah she'ein bo kezayit, you
have the head of a bird of
a turtle dove and it doesn't have a
כזית, kezayit, ומלח משלימה לכזית, u'melach mashlima l'kezayit, and the salt that
you dip it in makes it a כזית. kezayit. מהו? mahu? What's
the law? How would that help? Let's take a look. אמר ליה
רב פפא בר זיקא לרב אשי, Amar leh Rav Pappa bar Zeika
l'Rav Ashi, לאו היינו פלוגתא דרבי יוחנן וריש לקיש? lav haynu plugta
d'Rabbi Yochanan v'Resh Lakish? Wasn't that the exact debate of רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש? Resh Lakish? Things that you put up
on the מזבח mizbeach because you would normally salt things, right? לא
תשבית מלח ברית אלקיך מעל כל קרבנך תקריב מלח. lo tashbit melach
brit Elokecha me'al kol kurban'cha takriv melach. So things you would normally
put up together with a sacrifice that isn't the sacrifice itself, that
isn't the meat itself, it seems like it exactly plugs into that
debate.
No, because חיבור chibbur meaning it's like actually part of it.
Okay, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says no, תיבעי לרבי יוחנן תיבעי לריש לקיש. tiba'i l'Rabbi
Yochanan tiba'i l'Resh Lakish. No, this question could go either way regardless
of which position somebody took in the previous debate. תיבעי לרבי יוחנן,
Tiba'i l'Rabbi Yochanan, עד כאן לא קאמר רבי יוחנן התם, ad kan
lo ka'amar Rabbi Yochanan hatam, when did רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan say
the bone is part of it? אלא עצם, ela etzem, the bone,
דמינא דבשרא הוא, d'mina d'bisra hu, it's like an organic part of
the meat. I mean you say it's physically connected, but in addition
to physically connected, it's also like an organic part of the meat.
That's even more. אבל מלח דלאו מינא דבר יונה הוא, aval melach
d'lav mina d'bar yonah hu, salt which is clearly something that is
not organically part of the object, לא, lo, he would not be
considered to add to the כזית kezayit even though it would be
something that would be offered up together. תיבעי לריש לקיש, Tiba'i l'Resh
Lakish, and the question could also maybe it could go the other
way. עד כאן לא קאמר ריש לקיש התם, ad kan lo ka'amar
Resh Lakish hatam, אלא דאי פריש מיניה לאו מצוה לאסוקיה. ela d'ei
parish mineh lav mitzvah l'asukei. By the bone ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
said that's not considered to
add to the size because if the bone were to separate,
there'd be no obligation to put it up. So therefore it's never
per se being offered up because it's only being offered up because
it happens to be connected but it's only being schlepped with the
meat. Per se, the thing itself you would never put up. So
therefore even when it's going with the meat it's not considered something
that's offered. אבל הכא, aval hacha, but the salt, דאי פריש מצוה
לאסוקיה, d'ei parish mitzvah l'asukei, that if the salt falls off you
actually have to put salt back on. So this is obligated to
be offered. Yes, it's not the sacrifice, but it's obligated to be
offered and it is with the sacrifice, so לא, lo, או דילמא
לא שנא. o dilma lo shna. So maybe that would not be
like the bone and maybe that you would be חייב chayav or
maybe it shouldn't matter. תיקו. teiku. So we don't know which way
that goes. All right. That's point about that.
I mean, because like, then they could have come up with another
case like with if he offered up a horn or something like
that.
Yeah, that's a similar to the case of the בשר. basar.
No, but at least the בשר basar with the עצם, etzem, like,
I'm thinking...
well that seems that that would be obviously that you'd be פטור.
pattur. Clearly רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would not say you're חייב chayav
for the עצם. etzem. You're only חייב chayav for the בשר. basar.
Question is if it's משלים, mashlim, like
the horn and the,
okay, it seems that they would agree. I don't... okay, it seems
that they would agree with that. רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר. Rabbi Yose
HaGlili omer. Now רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili says, so the
issue came up here, רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili says you're
only חייב chayav for what the גמרא Gemara is calling מקדשי פנים.
mikudshai p'nim. You're only חייב chayav for when it's talking about שחיטה,
shechitah, you're חייב chayav for obviously you שחט shacht outside. But burning
up on the מזבח, mizbeach, for רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yose HaGlili,
it's only something that was שחט shacht in the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash because then the meat was fit for being burned on the
מזבח mizbeach and it has to be ראוי לפתח אהל מועד. ra'uy
l'petach ohel mo'ed. But he says if you שחט shacht it outside,
okay, you're never going to have one animal for רבי יוסי הגלילי
Rabbi Yose HaGlili that you're חייב chayav both for שחיטה shechitah and
מעלה ma'aleh because if you שחט shacht it outside then the meat
was never fit for being burned and then you're not חייב chayav
for it's not ראוי לפתח אהל מועד. ra'uy l'petach ohel mo'ed. And
the רבנן Rabbanan responded back and they said, no no no, but
but listen they said, even if you שחט shacht inside as soon
as you bring the meat outside you, it's פסול. passul. So you
have to concede that you're חייב chayav even if the meat is
not ראוי לפתח אהל מועד. ra'uy l'petach ohel mo'ed. So what difference
does it make if you שחט shacht inside or שחט shacht outside?
So that's what the רבנן rabbanan said to challenge רבי יוסי. Rabbi
Yosi. השיב רבי תחת רבי יוסי הגלילי. heshiv Rebbe tachas Rabbi Yosi
HaGlili. רבי Rebbe said, "Here, רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, let me take
this. Okay, I can respond to defend your position. There's a big
difference between shechting outside and it being פסול pasul because it was
shechted outside or being פסול pasul because you took it out after
it was shechted inside. מה לשוחט בפנים ומעלה בחוץ? mah l'shochet bifnim
u'ma'aleh bachutz? When you shechted it inside and then brought it out,
שעשתה לה שעת כושר, she'aysa lah sha'as kosher, for when at least
the meat at one stage was ראוי לפתח אהל מועד raui l'petach
ohel moed from the time it was shechted, even if it became
פסול pasul later. תאמר בשוחט בחוץ ומעלה בחוץ שלא היתה לו שעת
כושר? tomar b'shochet bachutz u'ma'aleh bachutz shelo haysa lo sha'as kosher? And
you're totally entitled to say you're not חייב chayav when you shechted
outside and then offered it up, because that meat was never fit
to being offered up." Okay. השיב רבי אלעזר בר שמעון תחת רבי
יוסי הגלילי. heshiv Rabbi Elazar bar Shimon tachas Rabbi Yosi HaGlili. רבי
אלעזר בר שמעון Rabbi Elazar bar Shimon says, "Here, רבי יוסי הגלילי,
Rabbi Yosi HaGlili, I'll defend you. מה לשוחט בפנים ומעלה בחוץ? mah
l'shochet bifnim u'ma'aleh bachutz? שכן קודש מקבלו. she'chein kodesh mekablo. When you
shechted it inside, even though you took it out, that פסול psul
did not totally disqualify it, because something that was יוצא yotzeh that
was brought back in and you put up on the מזבח, mizbeach,
right? That's one of the פסולים psulim that when you put it
on the מזבח mizbeach you don't take it off. So because that
was פסולה בקודש. psula bakodesh. תאמר בשוחט בחוץ שאין קודש מקבלו? tomar
b'shochet bachutz she'ein kodesh mekablo? When you shechted outside it wasn't פסולה
בקודש, psula bakodesh, and in that case if you put it on
the מזבח mizbeach it wouldn't accept it. So whereas רבי Rebbe says,
emphasizes there was a moment where it was fit, רבי אלעזר בר
שמעון Rabbi Elazar bar Shimon says it's even ראוי raui now if
you were to put it on the מזבח mizbeach it would be
allowed to stay." Okay, so two different reasons why רבי יוסי הגלילי'ס
Rabbi Yosi HaGlili's case makes sense that that case actually you're חייב
chayav and שחיטה shechita when it was shechted outside you wouldn't be
חייב. chayav מאי בינייהו? mai binaihu? Now what case would there be
that would be a difference between רבי'ס Rebbe's position and רבי אלעזר
בר שמעון? Rabbi Elazar bar Shimon? אמר זעירי, amar Zeiri, שחיטת לילה
איכא בינייהו. shechitas laila ika binaihu. If you shechted it at night,
if shechted in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, in that case it's
never had a שעת כושר, sha'as kosher, so for רבי Rebbe he
would say you'd be פטור. patur. אבל רבי אלעזר בר שמעון But
Rabbi Elazar bar Shimon would say it doesn't matter, that's a פסולה
בקודש psula bakodesh and if it would be put on the מזבח
mizbeach it would be allowed to stay there. So he would say
that meat would be considered ראוי raui and you'd be חייב. chayav
רבה אמר, Rabbah amar, קיבל בכלי חול איכא בינייהו. kibal b'kli chol
ika binaihu. So similar issue, you caught the blood in a כלי
חול. kli chol. Again, for רבי Rebbe it's not, it wouldn't have
a שעת כושר, sha'as kosher, so you would be פטור patur according
to רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yosi HaGlili, and for רבי אלעזר בר
שמעון Rabbi Elazar bar Shimon it would be a פסולה בקודש psula
bakodesh and it would be allowed to stay on the מזבח, mizbeach,
so you'd be חייב chayav according for רבי יוסי הגלילי. Rabbi Yosi
HaGlili. Okay, now טמא שאכל בין קודש. tamei she'achal ben kodesh. So
then the גמרא Gemara moved on to a similar debate between רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosi HaGlili and the חכמים hachamim about when you
are טמא. tamei. So if you're personally טמא tamei and eat a
קרבן, korban, you're חייב כרת. chayav kares. If the קרבן korban is
טמא tamei and you eat it, it's a לאו lav but it's
not כרת. kareis, So what if both you're טמא tamei and the
קרבן korban is טמא? tamei? So רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosi HaGlili
said, "Oh, you're not, you're פטור patur on כרת, kareis because you
didn't eat meat that was טהור." tahor. Right? The meat had already
been defiled. And the חכמים hachamim say, "But look, what's your case
רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yosi? It's the same, it's a parallel discussion. What's
your case רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi when the guy is טמא tamei
and then he's חייב כרת? chayav kares. He's טמא, tamei, he picks
it up and he eats it. So in that type of a
case, he already made the meat טמא. tamei. So even in the,
so you already concede that the normal case, both of them are
טמא. tamei. So why is that different from this case?" Now of
course you could get a scenario where you could eat it without
making the meat טמא. tamei. Somebody could put it in your mouth
and then it's נגיעה, negia, then it's you know, it's a נגיעת
בית הסתרים, negias beis hastarim, it's not considered like you touched it.
Okay, but presumably רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosi HaGlili doesn't limit his
פסק psak to that case. So then what's the difference if you're
טמא, tamei, you touch it and eat it, and you're חייב chayav
כרת, kareis or if it already was טמא tamei and then you
eat it? Either way you should be חייב chayav. כרת. kareis שפיר
קאמרי ליה רבנן לרבי יוסי הגלילי. shappir kamreiley rabbanan l'Rabbi Yosi HaGlili.
That was a good challenge, whereas before everybody came to רבי יוסי
הגלילי'ס Rabbi Yosi HaGlili's defense, here they're saying דקא, d'ka, it's a
good challenge, at the end of the day the meat is טמא
tamei when you eat it. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, כל היכא דנטמאה
טומאת הגוף ואחר כך נטמא בשר דכולי עלמא לא פליגי דחייב. kol
heicha d'nitma tumas haguf achar kach nitma basar d'chuley alma lo pligi
d'chayav. You're right. רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosi HaGlili does not say
in every case the meat is טמא tamei that you're not חייב
chayav. כרת. kares. It's really going to be a question about like,
about איסור חל על איסור. issur chal al issur. Okay, if you
start off as טמא, tamei, so right now I became טמא, tamei,
for me it would be a חיוב כרת hiyuv kares to eat
קדשים, kodshim, and then the piece of meat became טמא. tamei. It
doesn't change the fact that I already started in a status where
it was a חיוב כרת hiyuv kares for me to eat this
piece of meat and now just because it became טמא tamei that
doesn't change that and I'm going to be חייב chayav for eating
it. So it's not really the principle that as soon as the
meat becomes טמא tamei it's defiled and therefore it's impossible to be
חייב. chayav Because again, the rabbis made a good point: every time
you eat a קודש kodesh meat you're מטמא mitameh it and you're
חייב. chayav. So you're right, if you started off טמא tamei and
then it became the meat became טמא, tamei, whether you touched it
or somebody else touched it, you remain חייב chayav. כרת. kares, Everybody
agrees to that.
שכן טומאת הגוף בכרת she'kein tumas haguf b'kares because you started with
your חיוב כרת hiyuv kares and then this other thing came later
and obviously it doesn't depose it. כי פליגי בשנטמא בשר ואחר כך
נטמא הגוף. ki pligi b'shenitma basar v'achar kach nitma guf. First the
meat became defiled, טמא, tamei, and then I became
טמא. tamei. Okay, so and the issue here is not you can't
be חייב chayav for eating טמא tamei meat. We see that you
can be חייב chayav for eating טמא tamei meat. So what's the
issue? The issue is איסור חל על איסור. issur chal al issur.
The meat was already forbidden to me with a lower איסור, issur,
does the weightier איסור issur of כרת kares take place on top
of?
So will this איסור כרת issur kares I was already forbidden to
eat the meat because it was טמא, tamei, will I now also
be forbidden to it with the איסור כרת? issur kares? דרבנן סברי
מיגו, Derabbanan savrei migu, you say מיגו. migu. מיגו Migu means what?
מיגו Migu is, this is called an איסור כולל. issur kolel. When
I become טמא, tamei, I am now forbidden to eat all meat,
okay, not just this one piece of meat. All, all sacrificial meat.
So it started off that the only קרבן korban I was forbidden
to eat was this one that had become טמא. tamei. Now I
became טמא, tamei, I'm forbidden to eat all קרבנות, korbanos, even the
טהור tahor ones. So that's כולל, kolel, there's a larger scope. So
since it now this איסור כרת issur kares takes effect on those
other sacrifices, those טהור tahor ones, it also takes effect on this
one that is already טמא. tamei. So even though it is one
איסור issur layer, you know, layered on top of another one, that
can work because the second איסור issur has a broader scope and
takes effect on other things. That's מיגו. migu. Since it takes effect
on those, it takes effect on this. רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yossi
HaGlili סבר לא אמרינן מיגו, savar lo amrinan migu, we don't say
מיגו, migu, which is used other language means, we don't say איסור
חל על איסור issur chal al issur by an איסור כולל. issur
kolel. It doesn't matter that it has a broader scope, for רבי
יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yossi HaGlili, it doesn't take effect on top of
it. So now the גמרא Gemara says one minute, רבי יוסי, Rabbi
Yossi, אינה דמיגו לא אמרינן, inei demigu lo amrinan, תיתי טומאת הגוף
דחמירא וטהורה על טומאת בשר? teisei tumas haguf dechamira vetehora al tumas
basar? One minute, but we know elsewhere that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
says that you would say איסור כולל issur kolel if the second
איסור issur is weightier. So since the second איסור issur of טומאת
הגוף tumas haguf is weightier, it's כרת, kares, and its broader scope,
the combination of those two should say it should take effect on
top of the status of the meat. So אמר רב אשי, amar
Rav Ashi, ממאי דטומאת הגוף חמורה? mimai detumas haguf chamura? What makes
you say that that's weightier? Yes, it's true, it's כרת, kares, but
it's not a hundred percent weightier across the board. דילמא טומאת בשר
חמורה, Dilma tumas basar chamura, there's a way in which the טומאה
tumah of the meat is weightier. Which what is that? שכן אין
לה טהרה במקוה. shekein ein la tahara bemikvah. You can't change the
status of the meat. You can change the status of you as
a person. So since it's not, so since it's permanent on the
meat, and again, this to some degree makes sense for this הלכה,
halacha, because the question is does the new איסור issur take effect
on top of the meat, right? It's not just a broad question
of which is weightier. So if the issue is can this meat
that's already אסור assur because it's טמא tamei become אסור assur for
this other principle? The answer might be, you know what? That first
status is actually, as from the meat's perspective, that's actually weightier because
that status doesn't go off. So therefore, you know, from that perspective,
that is a weightier one and this second one, even though it's
broader and even though it's weightier in many other ways, does not
take effect for רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi on top of that. That's
sort of like somebody once reminded, said what's the line about what's
the difference between involved and committed? It's like when you make, when
you make like, the story was like ham and eggs. The chicken
is involved, the pig is committed. Yes.
So from anyway, the meat's perspective, it's committed. Its status is permanent.
I'm trying to understand how you see that explanation in the words
of the משנה. Mishnah. In other words, it seems that
no, it's not פשט pshat in the משנה Mishnah at all. But
it's the only way to defend רבי יוסי הגלילי. Rabbi Yossi HaGlili.
Okay, next משנה. Mishnah. חומר בשחיטה מהעלאה ובהעלאה מבשחיטה. Chomer beshchita meha'ala'ah
ubeha'ala'ah mibeshchita.
There are ways in which שחוטי חוץ shchutei chutz has weightier aspects
and there's ways in which העלאת חוץ, ha'alas chutz, or putting it
on the fire, has weightier aspects. חומר בשחיטה שהשוחט להדיוט חייב. Chomer
beshchita shehashocheit lehediot chayav.
Here's the question. The animal is sanctified, it's a קרבן. korban. When
I'm חייב chayav for שחיטה shechting it out of the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, here's an interesting point, right? שחיטה Shchita is not per
se a sacrificial act. Burning something on an altar is a sacrificial
act, okay? But שחיטה, shchita, I could be שחיטה shechting this because
we want to have a, we want to have a barbecue. So
Michael comes over to me and Michael says, "Hey Dov, you interested
in, you know, you want to have a steak tonight?" I said,
"Sure, the only problem is the only cow, you know, we don't
have lamb chops, the only lamb I got out back I sanctified
as a שלמים." shlamim. Eh, forget about it, let's just שחיטה shecht
it anyway and eat it. So we go ahead and we do
that. That's שחוטי חוץ. shchutei chutz. Even though you weren't doing it
as a sacrifice, the very fact that you took something that was
קדשים kodshim and שחיטה shechted it out of the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, you're חייב chayav even if you're שחיטה shechting it for the
purpose of eating its meat, even not as a sacrificial act. That's
a pretty big חידוש. chiddush.
Okay. So but the moment I took it isn't it מעילה me'ilah
and then?
Yeah, yeah, you might be over on מעילה me'ilah and a lot
of other things, but we're not dealing with it right now. I
mean if it's a שלמים, shlamim, that's less מעילה me'ilah issues, okay?
שהשוחט להדיוט חייב. Shehashocheit lehediot chayav.
And you don't say if it's מועל mo'el then it's יוצא לחולין.
yotzei lechullin. Right.
Anyway, again, let's,
yeah, it would be hard to be over
on, yeah, correct, but it's קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf you don't say
that. שהשוחט להדיוט חייב. Shehashocheit lehediot chayav. So once by שחוטי חוץ,
shchutei chutz, it's not about being a sacrificial act. It's about something
that was קדשים kodshim that was שחיטה shechted out of the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. והמעלה להדיוט פטור. Veha'ma'aleh lehediot patur. If I'm
going to go ahead and take this meat now and put it
on the fire and I'm going to do it either because I
want to have it as a barbecue or רש״י Rashi even goes
so far to mean מעלה להדיוט ma'aleh lehediot means I want to
offer it up to a person that I'm worshipping as a god,
okay, which is a pretty bad thing, you're חייב chayav for עבודה
זרה, avodah zarah, but you're not חייב chayav for העלאת חוץ. ha'alas
chutz. העלאת חוץ Ha'alas chutz is only when you offer It up
as a sacrificial act to God. Okay, so you might be חייב
chayav for עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, you might be חייב chayav for
putting meat of קדשי kodshei meat on as a barbecue, okay, but
you’re not חייב chayav for offering it. Offering it is only when
you offer it, so שחיטה shechita is שחיטה shechita for any purpose,
and העלאה ha'alah is only when it’s being put up there as
a sacrifice to God.
Okay. והמעלה להדיוט פטור. veha'aleh l'hedyot patur. חומר בעליה, chomer b'aliyah, now
here's how עליה aliyah is weightier, שנים שאחזו בסכין ושחטו פטורים. shnayim
she'achzu besakin veshachtu peturin. If two people did שחוטי חוץ shechutei chutz
combined, both holding the knife, they'd be exempt. אחזו באבר
והעלו חייבים. achzu b'eiver vehe'elu chayavin. But if two people jointly put
a piece of meat on the fire as a sacrificial act, they'd
be חייב. chayav. So there's no logic—there's logic to the שחיטה shechita
because again, שחיטה, shechita, as I said, is fundamentally not a sacrificial
act. There’s not a logic why with the question of partnership you're
חייב chayav more by העלאה ha'alah than by שחיטה. shechita. We'll see
it’s based on a פסוק. pasuk. Okay. העלה וחזר והעלה וחזר והעלה
חייב. he'ela chozar vehe'ela vechozar vehe'ela chayav. So let’s say you put
a, there’s different ways to read this, which the גמרא Gemara will
debate, but let's say it means I put—is this the same piece
of meat or different pieces? Let’s say it means different pieces of
meat. I'm putting up multiple pieces of meat from the same animal.
Okay. חייב על כל העלאה דברי רבי שמעון. chayav al kol aliyah
divrei Rabbi Shimon. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says if I put up
three, the four whatever legs of the cow, that's and I in
between each thing I remembered oh I'm not supposed to do this
and then I forgot again, that’s four separate transgressions.
Not if it’s the same piece of meat off and on?
That is—we'll see in the גמרא, Gemara, let's debate it, but let's
read it this way for now. Then that is going to be—then
that's חייב chayav for four separate transgressions, four separate קרבנות. korbanot. רבי
יוסי אומר אינו חייב אלא אחת. Rabbi Yose omer eino chayav ela
achas. No, if it’s all from the same cow, we'll read it
this way for now, it might be the same piece, the same
limb, but we’ll get to that later. If it’s all from the
same cow, you're not חייב chayav multiple times, you're only חייב chayav
once. We'll see why. ואינו חייב עד שיעלה לראש המזבח. v'eino chayav
ad she'ya'aleh l'rosh hamizbeach. Now Mike's question—Michael's asking—you're only חייב chayav when
you put this on the top of an altar. רבי שמעון אומר
Rabbi Shimon omer, אפילו העלה על סלע או על אבן חייב. chayav.
You don't need to construct an altar. Even if you put it
on a rock and I guess that you have to burn it
presumably, although that’s not clear, right? We're assuming that you have to
burn it, right? What does it mean? What if like you lay
it on a rock as an act of presenting it to God?
Okay, תעלה עולתיך. ta'aleh olatecha. I mean עולה, olah, right, normally we
say is fully consumed, right? But anyway, so that's not clear. So
it sounds, the literal meaning is just putting it on a rock
as a form of offering. Okay, so there anyway so that's two
questions: one question is do you need the structure of an altar,
and the other question is do you need to burn it?
Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. מאי שנא המעלה
להדיוט דפטור? mai shna hama'aleh l'hedyot d'patur? Why is somebody who offers
it up to a person—to a normal person—to a person, not to
God, why is that person exempt? דכתיב לה'. dichsiv l'Hashem. It says—the
פסוק pasuk is אל פתח אהל מועד לא יביאנו לעשות אותו לה'.
el petach ohel moed lo yevienu la'asos oso l'Hashem. You
didn’t—so you didn't bring it to אהל מועד ohel moed to make
it to God. So of course you could say but you did
it outside to עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. No, the reading is, but
you did it outside to God rather than in אהל מועד ohel
moed to God. The only variable is where it was, but the
act was that you were bringing it to God.
Okay. בשחיטה נמי כתיב לה'. bishchita nami ksiv l'Hashem. It says it's
also by שחיטה. shechita. אל פתח אהל מועד לא הביאו להקריב קרבן
לה'. el petach ohel moed lo hevi'o l'hakriv korban l'Hashem. Same thing.
שאני התם דאמר קרא איש איש. shani hasam d'amar kra ish ish.
When it starts by saying the prohibition of שחוטי חוץ, shechutei chutz,
it says any man, איש איש. ish ish. And איש איש ish
ish is being read, even when an איש ish offers it to
another איש, ish, okay, or does it for the sake of another
person. איש איש ish ish even then you'd be חייב. chayav Okay,
so גבי עולה נמי כתיב איש איש? gabei olah nami ksiv ish
ish? But it says sorry to spoil your party here, but when
it gets to being מעלה ma'aleh it also says איש איש ish
ish as well. So say it means even if you offer it
up to a man. No. מיבעי ליה לשנים שהעלו באבר חייבים. mibaya
lei l'shnayim she'he'elu b'eiver chayavin. So—no, איש איש ish ish means even
if two people are doing it in partnership. So by both of
them it says איש איש, ish ish, okay, but what do you
learn from איש איש? ish ish? איש איש ish ish you could
learn to mean if it’s offered to another man, done for the
sake of another person, or you could say it means if two
people do it together. So we split our vote. By שחיטה shechita
we say איש איש ish ish means you're חייב chayav, even if
you do it for the sake of another person, and by העלאה
ha'alah we say איש איש ish ish means only if—even if you
do it in partnership. And that's why that which is true for
one is not true for the other because you only get to
use איש איש ish ish one way for each דרשה. drasha. Of
course the גמרא's Gemara going to say what made you choose to
split it that way? Okay. אי הכי הכי נמי מיבעי ליה לשנים
שאחזו בסכין ושחטו חייבים? iy hachi hachi nami mibaya lei l'shnayim she'achzu
besakin veshachtu chayavin? Why not use the איש איש ish ish by
שחיטה shechita to say even if you do it together? No. שאני
התם דאמר קרא ההוא אחד ולא שנים. shani hasam d'amar kra hahu
echad v'lo shnayim.
It’s because the end of the פסוק pasuk is ונכרת האיש ההוא
מקרב עמו. v'nichras ha'ish hahu mikerev amo.
That man. So it's only—only an individual is חייב, chayav, two people
jointly are not חייב, chayav as it says by—by the case of
what do you call it—of שחיטה. shechita. So the גמרא Gemara says
גבי עולה נמי כתיב ההוא? gabei olah nami ksiv hahu? It also
says ההוא hahu by
העלאה, ha'alah, it says האיש ההוא ונכרת. ha'ish hahu v'nichras. So it's—
What you need this for is to say you're not חייב chayav.
if you were somehow forced to do this, the basic פטור ptur
of אונס, ones, like אונס רחמנא פטריה, ones rachmana patrei, which we
learn from לנערה לא תעשה דבר. l'na'ara lo ta'aseh davar. Sometimes we
learn it from the פסוק pasuk that
says ההוא, hahu, that you have to be in your right state
of mind to be חייב.
chayav Right, but שוגג, shogeg, you're פטור?
patur? Well, you're פטור patur from the כרת, karet, but you're
חייב חטאת.
chayav chatat. Same thing with anything
that you're חייב חטאת.
chayav chatat. Right. I mean, the more point is is about,
first of all תוספות Tosafot says, if you look at תוספות, Tosafot,
קצת קשה אונס למה לי קרא פשיטא דאונס רחמנא פטריה ושמא האונס
פרט לאומר מותר. ktzat kasheh ones lamah li kra pshita d'ones rachmana
patrei v'shema ha'ones prat l'omer mutar. Okay. Okay. And then הגמרא haGemara
says ותימא למה לי קרא למיפטרי מכרת כשהוא שוגג פשיטא בר קרבן
הוא? סלקא דעתך אמינא לאו מצי קרבן לא להוי בכרת. v'teima lamah
li kra l'miptrei mikaret k'shehu shogeg pshita bar korban hu? Salka da'atach
amina lav matzi korban lo lehvei b'karet. Okay, so some of this
stuff might have been clear from other ways, but anyway we learn
from ההוא hahu that you have to be in your right state
of mind. Okay. So by both of these it says here. Okay,
we'll erase this for now. So both of these it says, right,
איש איש, ish ish, what's the פסוק pasuk Michael? אשר ישחט.
asher yishchat. More? Which rather שוחט shochet one? Yeah. איש איש מבית
ישראל אשר ישחט שור או כשב או עז. ish ish mibit Yisrael
asher yishchat shor o kesev o ez.
Which is אשר ישחט. asher yishchat. Okay and then, and then it
says what, ונכרת האיש
ההוא.
v'nichrat ha'ish
hahu. Okay. And in this it says איש איש. ish ish.
Also
אשר יעלה עולה או זבח. asher ya'aleh olah o zavach.
אשר יעלה. asher ya'aleh. Okay.
אל פתח אהל מועד ונכרת
האיש ההוא.
el petach ohel mo'ed v'nichrat ha'ish
hahu.
So what we're saying is like this. Okay.
This איש איש ish ish tells me
whatever,
even a barbecue.
Well even for meat. Even, not yet barbecue, for another person. Okay.
This איש איש ish ish tells me two together.
Every single one of these things gets crossed out. Okay. Now why
not say this means two together? Because ההוא hahu says that you're
talking about just you have to be חייב chayav when you're
like only an individual.
So how about this ההוא? hahu? That should tell you only an
individual not two together? No, that tells you not אונס. ones. Okay,
but of course now the question is so how do you know
here not אונס? ones? Right? So let's take a look. So הגמרא
haGemara says אי הכי הכא נמי מיבעי ליה למיעוטי אונס שוגג ומוטעה?
i hachi hacha nami miba'ei lei l'mi'utei ones shogeg u'mut'eh?
So
by the case of שחיטה shechita you also need to exclude אונס?
ones? No, תרי ההוא כתיבי. trei hahu ktivi.
It says ההוא hahu twice because it says דם יחשב לאיש ההוא.
dam yeichashev la'ish hahu. Okay.
So because there's another, I think
דם יחשב dam yeichashev was before
the ונכרת. v'nichrat. לאיש ההוא. la'ish hahu.
So
since this ההוא hahu we know says not אונס, ones, we're left
with this ההוא hahu to say only an individual, so this can't
mean partnership. So this means even if you do it for another
person, even if you שחט shacht it just to eat the meat.
Whereas this you could say not אונס ones so you're allowed to
say איש איש. ish ish. I understand Michael, it's not, nobody has
ever said it was פשט. pshat. Okay. ואלא לה' למה לי? v'ela
l'Hashem lamah li? So if that's true, what's the point of לה'
l'Hashem by שחוטי חוץ? sh'chutei chutz? If you're חייב chayav even if
you don't bring it לה', l'Hashem, even if you're חייב chayav even
if you just שחט shacht it for the meat? להוציא שעיר משתלח.
l'hotzi sa'ir mishtale'ach.
To know, to talk about what type of קרבן korban it is.
It has to be a קרבן korban that was going לה'. l'Hashem.
If it was a קרבן korban that wasn't going לה' l'Hashem like
the שעיר משתלח sa'ir mishtale'ach which raises all of those of course
challenging theological ideas. So if you שחט shacht the שעיר משתלח sa'ir
mishtale'ach outside you're פטור patur because that was never going
לה'. l'Hashem. Alright. You could also just say why don't you just
say it wasn't ראוי לפתח אהל מועד. ra'uy l'petach ohel mo'ed. Anyway,
fine. Or maybe it started in פתח אהל מועד. petach ohel mo'ed.
חומר בהעלאה. chomer b'ha'ala'ah. Now we deal with the question about the
flip, which is העלאה ha'ala'ah and about two people together. תנו רבנן
איש איש. tanu rabanan ish ish. איש מה תלמוד לומר איש איש
מה תלמוד לומר לרבות שנים שאחזו באבר והעלו שחייבין. ish mah talmud
lomar ish ish mah talmud lomar l'rabot shnayim she'achazu b'eivar v'he'elu she'chayavin.
Even if they did in partnership. שהיה חל ולא דין הוא. shehayah
chal v'lo din hu. Make a קל וחומר kal vachomer to say
not. ומה שוחט להדיוט שחייב? u'mah shochet l'hediot she'chayav? And by the
case by שחיטה shechita we said that if you שחט shacht it
just for the meat you're חייב chayav and nevertheless שנים שאחזו בסכין
ושחטו פטורין, shnayim she'achazu b'sakin v'shachatu pturin, partnership
you're exempt. המעלה להדיוט שפטור. hamaleh l'hediot shepatur. By מעלה maleh which
we know it's weaker in that way that you're פטור patur if
you do it for an individual, only if you do it to
God. אינו דין ששנים שאחזו פטורין? eino din sheshnayim she'achazu pturin? It
should be weaker across the board, even two people in partnership? תלמוד
לומר איש איש דברי רבי שמעון. talmud lomar ish ish divrei Rabi
Shimon. איש איש ish ish means even in partnership. רבי יוסי אומר
ההוא אחד ולא שנים. Rabi Yosi omer hahu echad v'lo shnayim. No,
he disagrees. He says that this ההוא. hahu. Who knows where he
gets אונס, ones, maybe he gets it from לנערה לא תעשה דבר.
l'na'ara lo ta'aseh davar. But the same way this ההוא hahu up
here excluded the idea of partnership, this ההוא hahu excludes the idea
of partnership. He disagrees with this פסק. psak.
Because אונס ones you're always פטור. patur.
I understand. I understand, that's what I just said. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says, so אם כן מה תלמוד לומר איש איש? im
ken mah talmud lomar ish ish? What do you get from איש
איש? ish ish? דיברה תורה כלשון בני אדם. Dibrah Torah kilshon bnei
adam. Yeah, that's just, you know, a way of talking. Of course
what that doesn't explain is that how we are entitled to דרשן
darshen that this איש איש ish ish to mean even if you
just do it, you know, for an individual and for the meat.
Anyway, ורבי שמעון האי ההוא מיבעי ליה למיעוטי שוגג אונס ומוטעה. v'Rabbi
Shimon hai hahu mibaya lei limutei shogeg ones u-mutah. And Rabbi Shimon
would say like we said before, no ההוא hahu doesn't tell me
an individual, it tells me to exclude the case of being deceived
or being forced etc. ורבי יוסף מיהו ההוא. v'Rabbi Yosef mi hu
hahu. It could have said איש הוא. ish hu. It says ההוא.
hahu. Of course that would have been grammatically wrong. ורבי שמעון הוא
ההוא לא דרש, Rabbi Shimon hu hahu lo darshe, fine. ורבי יוסף
מדיהאי איש איש דיברה תורה כלשון בני אדם ההוא איש איש נמי
דיברה תורה כלשון בני אדם, v'Rabbi Yosef mida'hai ish ish dibrah torah
kilshon bnei adam, hahu ish ish nami dibrah torah kilshon bnei adam,
so we're back to this. So if he says this איש איש
ish ish is דיברה תורה כלשון בני אדם dibrah torah kilshon bnei
adam and he doesn't believe that you're חייב chayav in partnership here
too, this איש איש ish ish should just be normal way of
speaking. And how do you know the idea that even if you're
not doing it as a sacrifice? אלא השוחט להדיוט מנלן דחייב? ela
hashocheit l'hedyot minalan d'chayav? How do you know you're חייב chayav even
if you're not doing it as a sacrifice? נפקא ליה מדם יחשב
לאיש ההוא דם שפך. nafkah lei mi-dam yeichasheiv la'ish hahu dam shafach.
So it's דם לאיש. dam la'ish.
So okay, even if the blood was done for the sake of
a man, even if the blood was spilled for the sake of
a person and not for God.
ואפילו השוחט לאיש. v'afillu hashocheit la'ish. Come on, it's a דרשה. drasha.
Okay. Okay. Now to the more, the less clear part of the
משנה, mishnah, this debate about whether if you do it multiple times
are you חייב chayav for having done it for multiple עבירות. aveirot.
And the נפקא מינה nafka mina would be, I mean I you
know could be that you were warned and you get מלקות malkus
multiple times but the חייב chayav here basically means it was בשוגג,
b'shogeg, do you bring multiple קרבנות korbanot if you became aware in
the middle. Now Michael is correct that I don't know if he's
correct but it was certainly the way he read the משנה mishnah
was the way I would have initially have read the משנה mishnah
which means that it's the same piece of meat. העלה וחזר והעלה.
heila v'chazar v'heila. It falls off and you put it back on,
it falls off and you put it back on. Okay, but that
is not the way the גמרא Gemara is going to read it.
Let's see the way the גמרא Gemara is going to read it.
And there's a debate רש"י Rashi תוספות Tosafot here I'm going to
follow תוספות's Tosafot's read which is easier.
Okay, העלה וחזר והעלה. heila v'chazar v'heila. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אמר ריש לקיש, amar Reish Lakish, מחלוקת בארבע והי איברים. machlokes b'arba
v'hei evarim. The debate is, you know, separate limbs. We're putting each
one of the legs on the מזבח mizbeiach at a separate time.
Is that a separate עבירה aveirah or is it the same עבירה
aveirah done multiple times? Okay.
Or well we'll see exactly what they, maybe that's even not the
right way to say it. דמר סבר כי כתיב לעשות אותו להשם,
d'mar savar ki ksiv la'asot oto l'Hashem, to make to do it
for God, על השלם הוא חייב ואינו חייב על
החסר. al hashalem hu chayav v'eino chayav al hachaser. So רש"י Rashi
doesn't tell you the way רש"י Rashi reads it but then we're
going to go to תוספות's Tosafot's reads. תוספות Tosafot reads you're not
חייב chayav until... the way רש"י Rashi reads it, excuse me, is
you're not חייב chayav until you offer the whole animal up. So
therefore he says when you do individual limbs you're not חייב chayav
multiple times because you're only חייב chayav at the end. You're only
חייב chayav. if the whole animal made it up on the מזבח,
mizbeiach, which is a pretty radical read which means that I could
put up 98% of the animal and still not be חייב. chayav
So that's why רש"י Rashi reads. We're going to bracket that. תוספות
Tosafot reads על השלם הוא חייב, al hashalem hu chayav, you're only
חייב chayav. when the offering is coming from a whole animal. So
you שחט shecht the animal, it starts as שלם, shalem, and you
put a כזית k'zayit on the altar. That's when you're חייב. chayav
Okay. Whereas if after the first כזית k'zayit you're going to be
פטור patur for everything else, after that it's not שלם shalem anymore.
Okay. Right, right, isn't that...
so we're not saying על השלם al hashalem as opposed to like
a בעל מום ba'al mum or whatever?
No, no, just means the whole and not the... בעל מום ba'al
mum is an interesting catch question, we're not up to there yet,
okay, we'll get there.
Anyway it has to be בראוי לפתח אהל מועד bra'ui l'petach ohel
mo'eid remember. So therefore, so על...
where was it? דמר סבר כי כתיב לעשות אותו la'asot oto על
השלם הוא חייב chayav ואינו חייב chayav על החסר, so you can't
be חייב chayav for the other ones because it's חסר chaser after
the first, after the first limb was put up.
על כל בהמה כתיב. al kol behemah ksiv. So that לעשות אותו
la'asot oto refers to the whole animal, the whole animal has to
be שלם. shalem. And as soon as it's not שלם, shalem, you're
פטור patur after the first limb went up. ומר סבר על כל
איבר ואיבר כתיב. u'mar savar al kol eivar v'eivar ksiv. No, לעשות
אותו oso. means each individual limb. So if you broke a limb
into two halves for example you wouldn't be חייב chayav on the
second half of a limb. Okay, but so look at each limb,
each limb it's when you offer it up from a שלם shalem
limb. But the animal you don't have to offer it from a
בהמה שלימה. behemah shleimah. All right, so that's that's that debate. So
the point is after some of the animal has begun to be
offered up, are you חייב chayav for the rest because the animal
is no longer שלם. shalem. אבל איבר אחד דברי הכל אינו חייב
אלא אחת. aval eivar echad divrei hakol eino chayav ela achas. If
you took one limb and did it in two halves, you know
first a כזית... k'zayit... multiple times? No. One limb and doing it
we're maintaining the sense that it's new meat being put up, okay,
but by the time you got to the second half of the
limb, that limb wasn't שלם. shalem. Okay so everybody agrees it has
to come from something שלם, shalem, the question is does it have
to come from a בהמה שלימה behemah shleimah and you're only חייב
chayav on the first part of the animal that was offered up,
or does it have to come from a שלם shalem limb and
you're only חייב chayav from the first part of a limb that
was offered? But if you did a different limb, you definitely...
Would that be the same thing with a regular קרבן? korban? Let's
say I'm a person who's not allowed to do the עבודה avoda
and I did it for half a limb and I did it
for the other half of a limb and it's—
oh no, I don't think we divide it that way. It's like
any עבודה. avoda. I mean, it's a good question, that's— okay, so
what happens? Do you go by כזית kezayit or whatever? But no,
it has— there's no idea of that שלם shalem by the חיוב
chiyuv of the זר. zar. Okay. רבי יוחנן אמר מחלוקת באבר אחד.
Rabbi Yochanan amar machlokes be'ever echad. No, the debate is within one
limb. Whether whether that limb has to be whole.
דמר סבר מוקטרי פנים שחסרו והעלה בחוץ חייב demar savar muktarei penim
shechasru vehe'ela bachutz chayav that some and here the reason is because
if it was
offered
inside the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, okay, then like was שחט shachted
in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, then the thing that's now fit
to be on the מזבח mizbeach even a partial limb is fit
to be on the מזבח. mizbeach. Okay, so since if we're dealing
with something that was שחט shachted in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
חייב chayav even on a partial limb.
Yes, it's true you might need whole when it was שחט shachted
let's say out of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. But שחט shachted
in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, since even a partial limb you
put on the מזבח, mizbeach, חייב chayav even on a partial limb
outside. ומר סבר פטור. umar savar patur. Okay, so according to him
אבל באבר ואיבר דברי הכל חייב על כל אבר ואבר. aval be'ever
va'ever divrei hakol chayav al kol ever va'ever. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says everybody agrees the animal doesn't have to be whole. The
only point is the limb has to be whole. And actually if
it was שחט shachted outside, everybody agrees the limb has to be
whole. And when you got to part two of the limb, you'd
be פטור. patur. What's the debate? The debate was when it was
שחט shachted inside. One is of the opinion that, okay, it's still
the same, you're only חייב chayav. on a whole limb, and the
other says no, because this was שחט shachted inside you're חייב chayav
even on a partial limb because because this meat in the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash you'd put up even if it wasn't whole.
So follows like what אביי Abaye says so to speak, right, since
in the בית המקדש— Beis Hamikdash yeah, exactly.
Okay, ופליגא דעולא. upliga d'Ulla. Now this read of רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan argues on עולא. Ulla. דאמר עולא הכל מודים במוקטרי פנים שחסרו
והעלה בחוץ שחייב. d'amar Ulla hakol modim b'muktarei penim shechasru vehe'ela bachutz
shechayav. He says no, everybody would agree that if it started in
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you're חייב chayav on a partial limb
for exactly that reason because in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash even
a partial limb goes up. Okay,
לא נחלקו אלא במוקטרי בחוץ. lo nechelku ela b'muktarei bachutz. The only
debate is when it was שחט shachted outside שחסרו והעלה בחוץ. shechasru
vehe'ela bachutz. דמר סבר פטור, demar savar patur, you're exempt because it
has to be a whole limb and by by the time you
get to part two of the limb, you're exempt.
ומר סבר חייב, umar savar chayav, and the other one says you're
חייב. chayav, He basically maybe doesn't hold to this whole דרשה, drasha,
you're חייב chayav on a partial limb, end of story. איכא דאמרי,
ika d'amri, some say אמרו לעולא הכל מודים במוקטרי בחוץ שחסרו והעלה
בחוץ שהוא פטור. amru l'Ulla hakol modim b'muktarei bachutz shechasru vehe'ela bachutz
shehu patur. No, the opposite, but whatever, a different degree of debate.
Okay, no, on the outside everybody agrees that it has to be
a whole limb.
Okay, that's the אותו. לא נחלקו אלא במוקטרי פנים. lo nechelku ela
b'muktarei penim. They're debating about when it was offered on the inside
שחסרו והעלה בחוץ. shechasru vehe'ela bachutz. דמר סבר פטור, demar savar patur,
one holds you're exempt, same הלכה, halacha, it always needs to be
a whole limb, so the second part of the limb you're exempt.
ומר סבר חייב, umar savar chayav, no, you're still חייב chayav on
the second part of the limb because you would since it was
שחט shachted inside, that second part of the limb would go up
on the מזבח mizbeach inside. Okay, and therefore that is exactly what
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says. ופליגא דאבוה דשמואל אלישנא קמא דעולא. upliga
d'avua d'Shmuel al lishna kama d'Ulla.
The father of שמואל Shmuel disagrees with the first approach of עולא.
Ulla. The first approach of עולא Ulla says that everybody agreed by
the inside case, the debate was by the outside case. How do
you know that? דאמר אבוה דשמואל כמאן מדלינן פקועין לגבי מזבח. d'amar
avua d'Shmuel keman madlinan pekuin legabei mizbeach. According to whose פסק psak
do we put things that fall off of the מזבח mizbeach back
on? Now this is like hilarious because the phrase כמאן keman do
we do X means according to whose פסק psak are we following
in our current practice when we do X, Y, and Z? Okay,
like when the גמרא Gemara says like, you know, in the debate
of like whether בתשרי נברא עולם be'Tishrei nivra olam or בניסן נברא
עולם, be'Nissan nivra olam, it says כמאן מצלינן— keman matzlinan you know,
according to who do we pray nowadays when we say היום הרת
עולם? Hayom harat olam? You know, so normally it's כמאן keman do
we do X האידנא ha'idna nowadays. So thankfully at least this גמרא
Gemara didn't have האידנא, ha'idna, but it's still pretty funny the way
it's phrased. According to whom do we do this? What do you
mean do we do this? Anyway, okay, according to whom do we
say that if something falls off the altar you put it back
on? Which means which reflects an idea that in the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash even a partial limb goes back on. כמאן דלא כרבי
יוסי, keman dela k'Rabbi Yosi, not like רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, because
why? Since רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi said that, now I forget who
said what, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi said you're not חייב, chayav you
know, you're
only חייב chayav once. So he's reading it as you're not חייב
chayav on the second part of the limb. And why are you
not חייב chayav on the second part of the limb? So if
it was something that was שחט shachted inside you should be חייב
chayav on the second part of the limb. No, it must mean
that according to רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi actually a partial limb that
flew off you would not put back on. Okay, so therefore he's
saying that, you know, so anyway that reflects the idea that he's
understanding that the debate is about stuff that's שחט shachted on the
inside and therefore and the debate is the only reason to say
you'd be פטור patur on a partial limb if it was שחט
shachted inside is if you say even in the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash if a partial limb fell off you wouldn't put it back
on. And that's and that is okay fine and that's the way
he understands the debate. Okay, ואינו חייב עד שיעלה. ve'eino chayav ad
sheya'ale. Now,
so that was very interesting. questions about, you know, do you need
the animal to be whole, do you need the limb
to be whole, difference between שחט shechted inside, שחט shechted outside. And
now the last debate about what are you putting it on? Are
you putting it on an altar, are you putting on a rock?
Okay, so אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, מאי טעמא דרבי יוסי?
mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Yosi? What's the reason of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi
that says you need an altar? דכתיב, de-chsiv, ויבן נח מזבח להשם.
Vayiven Noach mizbei'ach l'Hashem. So you see that when people are bringing
things outside of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, and it's so funny
context of the פסוק, pasuk, I mean, you know, there's tons of
places people are bringing things outside the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, but
anyway, but here's, but the point I guess is that it literal,
it says he built it. So the implication is he wouldn't be
allowed to bring it outside the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash without it
being a מזבח. mizbei'ach. So, and you can sort of somehow infer
what is you need, this is a fascinating idea too. You can
infer what makes it a sacrifice when במות bamos are permissible to
that would actually be what you're חייב chayav for when במות bamos
are forbidden. Okay, so, you know, if something was always forbidden, if
let's say even when במות bamos were permissible, you're not allowed to
bring something on a rock, so that was always never considered an
acceptable offering to God, so then even when במות bamos are forbidden,
you're not חייב chayav for העלאת חוץ. ha'alas chutz. It's similar to
the same way if you do it as an עבודה זרה avodah
zarah you're not חייב chayav. for העלאת חוץ. ha'alas chutz. It's something
different, okay? But העלאת חוץ ha'alas chutz is something that would have
been a sacrificial act to God and this is also to God,
but it's outside and it's still a sacrificial act because it's done
in the way that would have been accepted when במות bamos were
permissible. But if it were done in a way that would not
have been accepted when במות bamos are permissible, then presumably that gets
you out of the category. So you see if נח Noach needed
a מזבח, mizbei'ach, we need a מזבח mizbei'ach to be חייב chayav?
for העלאת חוץ.
ha'alas chutz. What's interesting is, you know, I just went back a
little further, it doesn't say anywhere by קין והבל Kayin v'Hevel that
they had a מזבח.
mizbei'ach. So maybe we took the first example. Right. אמר רבי יוחנן,
Amar Rabbi Yochanan, מאי טעמא דרבי שמעון? mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Shimon? So
what's the reason of רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon דכתיב, de-chsiv, ויקח מנוח
את גדי העזים ואת המנחה ויעל על הצור להשם. Vayikach Manoach es
gdi ha-izim v'es ha-mincha vaya'al al ha-tzur l'Hashem. Okay,
so there you see he did something, he did it right on
the rock. ואידך V'idach נמי, nami, והא כתיב ויבן מזבח להשם? v'ha
ksiv Vayiven mizbei'ach l'Hashem?
What do you do about the fact that it seems like נח
Noach needed it? ההוא גובהא בעלמא. Hahu govha b'alma. That's just a
height. Now it sounds like you're saying, it doesn't sound like it
was constructed, it sounds like it just meant like on a little
hill, but no, רש"י Rashi doesn't say that. רש"י Rashi just says,
כדרך כל הארץ שנוח להשתמש ולא לחובת מזבח. kederech kol ha-aretz she-noach
l'hishtamesh v'lo l'chovas mizbei'ach. No,
it's true he built it, but he didn't build it because it
was somehow ritually required. He built it because that was the norm,
because that was convenient. Who wants to bend down on a rock?
You got a bad back anyway or whatever. Okay, fine, he did
it for convenience, it's not a proof of anything. ואידך V'idach נמי,
nami, הכתיב ויקח מנוח? ha ksiv Vayikach Manoach?
Okay, but by מנוח Manoach it seems like God accepted it even
though it was on a rock. הוראת שעה הייתה. Hora'as sha'ah haysah.
That was a special exception. ואיבעית אימא, V'ibayis eima, היינו טעמא דרבי
שמעון, hainu ta'ama de-Rabbi Shimon, here's the reason of רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon? כדתניא, K'disanya, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. אומר, מזבח, mizbei'ach, because maybe
we're a little bit bothered, let's see, מזבח פתח אהל מועד ואין
מזבח בבמה. mizbei'ach pesach Ohel Mo'ed v'ein mizbei'ach b'bamah.
The same idea. You're only חייב chayav for חוץ chutz what you're
allowed to do by a במה. bamah. So since it says מזבח
פתח אהל מועד, mizbei'ach pesach Ohel Mo'ed, so therefore the פסוק pasuk
is what's the פסוק? pasuk? וזרק הכהן את הדם על מזבח השם
פתח אהל מועד. v'zarak ha-kohen es ha-dam al mizbei'ach Hashem pesach Ohel
Mo'ed.
So only in אהל מועד Ohel Mo'ed do you need a מזבח.
mizbei'ach. When there's no מקדש, Mikdash, you don't even need a מזבח.
mizbei'ach. If you're for במה, bamah, you don't even need a במה
bamah for a במה, bamah, you can just put it on a
rock. לפיכך, Lefikach, and because, העלה על הסלע על האבן חייב. he'ela
al ha-sela al ha-even chayav.
Therefore you're חייב. chayav So the גמרא Gemara says, what do you
mean חייב? chayav You're trying to tell me what's permissible for a
במה. bamah. יצא מיבעי ליה. yatza mibai lei. You should be saying
therefore when you're in the time of במות, bamos, you could be
יוצא yotzei even without a מזבח. mizbei'ach. So the גמרא Gemara says,
הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, yes, but that's what it means. It's a
two-step argument. לפיכך, Lefikach, בשעת איסור במות, besha'as issur bamos, because you're
יוצא yotzei when it's בשעת היתר במות besha'as heter bamos without a
מזבח, mizbei'ach, therefore at the time of איסור במות, issur bamos, העלה
על הסלע או על האבן חייב. he'ela al ha-sela o al ha-even
chayav.
So again, the fascinating thing, something that would have always not been
acceptable is not you're not חייב chayav for doing it בחוץ. bachutz.
You're only חייב בחוץ bachutz the institution of trying to do a
במה להשם בחוץ. bamah l'Hashem bachutz. If you're trying to do something
that never would have been recognized as an acceptable form of worshipping
God, or חס ושלום, chas v'shalom, you're even worshipping, you know, עבודה
זרה, avodah zarah, that's a different issue, that is not שחוטי חוץ.
shchutei chutz.
איבעיא ליה לרבי יוסף בר חנינא, Iba'aya lei l'Rabbi Yosef bar Chanina,
now רבי יוסף בר חנינא Rabbi Yosef bar Chanina asked: קרן וכבש
ויסוד וריבוע, keren v'kevesh v'yesod v'ribu'a, מהו שיעכבו בבמה? mahu she-ya'akvu b'bamah?
So if you need a מזבח mizbei'ach for a במה, bamah, do
you need all of the what defines a מזבח? mizbei'ach? Does it
have to have horns, does it have to have a ramp, does
it have to have a base, does it have to be square?
It's a good question, right? Like I'm sure you open up your
Biblical Archaeological Review and you look at, like, ancient altars, my guess
is they all probably were a similar type of, you know, or
whatever, rectangular or square with a base. I don't know if they
all had horns, a lot of them did. Anyway, so if you
need an altar, what defines an altar for במה bamah to be
מותר muttar for במה bamah or to be חייב for שחוטי חוץ?
shchutei chutz? אמר ליה רב ירמיה תניא, Amar lei Rav Yirmeya tanya,
we taught the answer to a ברייתא: braisa: קרן וכבש Keren v'kevesh
וריבוע veribu'a ויסוד veyesod מעכבין meakvin בבמה גדולה. bevama gedola. That was
needed in like the במה גדולה, Bama Gedola, like in נוב Nov
and גבעון, Gibeon, okay, communal במות, bamot, okay, even at a time
of like, you know, whatever, when you didn't have a בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, ואין מעכבין בבמה קטנה. ve'ein meakvin bevama ketana. But no,
but it's, but for a normal private במה Bama you don't need
it, and therefore you also don't need it to be חייב for
שחוטי shichutei and העלאת חוץ. ha'ala'as chutz.